Professor Farouq A. Renjbal, M.D., Ph.D.

Public Health Physician/Consultant

136 Eric Maloney Way, Ottawa, Ontario K1T 0R1, Canada Email: 2211hisha@gmail.com, Phone: 1-514-991-9262

CAREER OBJECTIVE

Interested in Management/Consulting level position that utilizes my skills and creativity in the field of Medicine.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Drugs and addiction are very detrimental to social, economic and family life because they cause divorce, homelessness and financial and health deterioration. Therefore, I am very much interested in working in the field of Rehabilitation and Treatment of Drug Users and Alcoholics, specifically Drug Abuse and Alcoholic Addiction Rehabilitation of adolescents and youth by using psychological and pharmacological approaches, adding follow-up awareness and preventive sessions on an ongoing basis, and holding seminars and cultural lectures for various classes of society to acquaint them with the damage resulting from abuse and addiction to their economic, health, family and social life.

As a Consultant in the Eastern Province of Saudi Arabic for the last 13 years, I conducted a research about the disposal of industrial water in the sea and its effects on the health of consumers.

While working at the University of Aleppo, I conducted research on how to get rid of toxic substances used in pigments for wool and leather, and in chemical plants in general. Basically, my research interest is focused on the examination and detection of food poisons and toxins, i.e. the presence of chemicals in the atmosphere, in food and drink, in the environment, or in chemical leaks such as leaks caused by toxic gases and chemicals. My study entitled Examination and Detection of Food Poisons and Toxins covers the poorest areas in the world that use chemicals without having an up-to-date scientific information. My research highlighted the current environmental practices and offers alternative methods and solutions to act environmentally and hygienically in order to get rid of toxic substances at the human, industrial and agricultural levels.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

2005-2017: Chief of Public Health Department, King Fahd Hospital, Houfuf, Saudi Arabia.

- Planned and controlled departmental budget.
- Planned, organized, directed, controlled and evaluated the delivery of health care services as the Chief of Public Health Department.

Professor F. Renjbal Page 1 of 3

- Consulted with boards of directors and senior managers to establish and maintain standards for the provision of health care services.
- Developed evaluation systems to monitor the quality of provided health care.
- Monitored the use of diagnostic services, in-patient beds, and facilities to ensure effective use of resources.
- Developed and implemented plans for new programs, special projects, new material and equipment acquisitions and future staffing levels in the department.
- Supervised health care professionals and recruited new staff of the department.
- Represented the department at meetings with government officials, the public and the media.

2005-2012: Assistant-Professor of Medicine, University of Aleppo, Aleppo, Syria.

1988-2005: Physician, Technical Head of Pharmacy Department and Head of the External Clinic of the University Hospital, Aleppo, Syria.

HONORS, AWARDS & RECOGNITIONS

- Recipient of the 1997 Ministry of Health Award for the book: The Effectiveness Rapid Interventions to Save the Injured in Road Accidents on the Road between Aleppo and Damascus.
- Recipient of 2016 King Fahd Hospital Research Award for the work on Coronavirus Prevention and Sterilization.
- Certificate of Appreciation (2015), King Fahd Hospital for the tangible efforts to control and reduce the spread of MERS-coronavirus in Al-Ahsa, Saudi Arabia.
- Certificate of Appreciation (2014). The Directorate of Health Affairs in Al-Ahsa Province for the Effective Participation in the Steam Disinfection of Facilities and Hospitals during the Outbreak of MERS coronavirus (MERS-CoV) in 2014.
- Certificate of Appreciation (2008), Management of the General Medical Committee, King Fahd Hospital, for the exemplary commitment, sincerity and dedication to work at the General Medical Committee from 2005 to 2008 and for the supervision of Clinic No. 5 allocated for pre-marriage examination, prospective expatriate labor personnel, and professionals and students medical examination.

EDUCATION

- Doctorate of Medicine, Russian Academy of Medical Science (RAMS), Moscow, 2001.
- Doctor of Medicine (M.D.) degree, the University of Aleppo, Aleppo, Syria, 1988.
- Two year **specialization in Thoracic Diseases**, 1992

Professor F. Renjbal Page 2 of 3

PUBLICATIONS AND CONFERENCE PARTICIPATION

- Renjbal, Farouq A. (2014-2016). Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS-CoV), also known as Camel Flu: Prevention Methods and Sterilization of Homes. Presented during a workshop on infection control in the King Fahd Hospital and is based on my clinical follow-up (57 pages) on coronavirus in patients and on residents living with coronavirus patients at home (203 pages).
- Renjbal, Farouq A. (2003): "Public Health and the Human Environment, First Edition", Book (430 pages), Aleppo, Syria. Al-Noor Press.
- Supervising Professor of a thesis "The Effect of Fluoride on Dental Health in Different Areas in Syria Where Chlorine is either high or low", Aleppo, Syria. Al-Nour Press, 2003.
- Renjbal, Farouq A. (2001). Booklet on How to Admit Patients from outside Clinics into the Departments of the University Hospital. Aleppo, Syria. Aleppo University Press.
- A workshop on the methodology of the Pharmacy Department at Aleppo University Hospital to Prevent Errors in Dispensing Medications (2000). Speaker.
- Renjbal, Farouq A. (1997). The Effectiveness of Rapid interventions to Save the Injured in Road Accidents on the Road between Aleppo and Damascus, First Edition, Ministry of Health, Damascus, Syria. And also presented in Aleppo University Scientific Conference (1997). "Road Accidents between Aleppo and Damascus." Speaker.
- A workshop for the Emergency Department at Aleppo University Hospital to Reduce the Waiting Time of Patients (1996). Speaker.

ACCREDITATION AND PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATION

- Public Health Consultant, Saudi Commission for Health Specialties, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, since 2010.
- Member of the Committee on Natural Disaster in the Eastern Region of Saudi Arabia, since 2007.
- Member of the Syrian Syndicate of professors since 2006.
- Member of the Syria Medical Association since February 27, since 1990.

SUMMARY OF ADDITIONAL QUALIFICATIONS

- Multilingual skills: fluency in Arabic & Russian; working knowledge of English.
- Strong written and verbal communication skills.
- · Ability to learn new procedures quickly.
- Knowledge of online and printed reference tools useful for medicine and research.
- Ability to work independently, meet deadlines and achieve results.
- Attention to details with excellent organization skills & computer skills.

Professor F. Renjbal Page 3 of 3